<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poore mans cry Wherein is shevved the present miserable estate of mee Iohn Lilburne, close prisoner in the fleete. Also an humble petition to his Maiesties honorable privy councill, for meantenance that I famish not.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15598</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112218</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847476</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1604:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poore mans cry Wherein is shevved the present miserable estate of mee Iohn Lilburne, close prisoner in the fleete. Also an humble petition to his Maiesties honorable privy councill, for meantenance that I famish not.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richt Right Press] Published by a backe friend of the English popish prelates,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some pages cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prisoners' writings, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12513:1"/>
            <p>THE POORE MANS CRY. Wherein <hi>Is ſhevved the preſent miſerable eſtate of mee IOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE, Cloſe priſoner in the Fleete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO An humble Petition to his Maieſties Honorable privy Councill, for meantenance that I famiſh not.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 21.13.</bibl> Who ſo ſtoppeth his eares at the cry of the poore, he alſo himſelfe ſhall cry and not be heard.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Publiſhed by a backe friend of the Engliſh Popiſh Prelates, 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12513:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not without the ſpecial wiſdome of God, to ſet forth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt vnder the name &amp; title of <hi>a Beaſt:</hi> For looke as <hi>Beaſts</hi> do exerciſe all kinde of cruelty, and no favour is to be expected from them: ſo it is with the inhuman <hi>Prelates,</hi> their delight is only <hi>in the blood of the</hi> Saints: and as for <hi>Pittie, Compaſſion, Charritie &amp;c.</hi> there is no more in them then in Dogs. I could giue many inſtances
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Witnes lately their offering of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds to one in London, to betray his friend into their bloody hands.</p>
                  <p>It ſeemes there is now ſome ſcarſity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe Wolues, that they will giue ſoe much monie for one poore ſheep.</p>
               </note> of their <hi>beaſt-like</hi> doings this way: but it needs not, conſidering how the ſame is already knowne vnto all men in all places. Beſides in this ſhort Relation, thou ſhalt haue as much proued as I do here affirme of them: namely that they are without naturall affections, inhumane, barberous. Such as <hi>Pleaſe not God, and are contrarie to all men 1 Theſſ,</hi> 2.15. fulfilling herein (as did Iudas) the Propheſies recorded of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Revelation, viz. to be <hi>Serpents, Scorpions,</hi> and the <hi>Spirits of Divels,</hi> making warre againſt the Saints and to overcome them.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of whoſe cruelty, is to advertiſe euery faithfull man, to looke to it, that he well prepare himſelfe; to fight with theſe <hi>Beaſts,</hi> that ſo whenſoever the Lord ſhall call him to warree this way, he may by the power of the <hi>Lambe</hi> overcome, and poſseſſe the Crowne of life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy exiled friend and nameleſſe Country-man.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12513:2"/>
            <head>To all the people of God, that loue the Lord Ieſus Chriſt in truth and ſincerity, and deſire the vvelfare and proſperity of his poore afflicted Saints &amp; Seruants.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earely beloued Brethren, and fellow heires of the ſame Kingdome and Crowne of Glory with mee. I am at this preſent conſtrained to declare vnto
<note n="(a)" place="margin">If we will be like vnto God we must haue our eares open to heare the cry of the oppreſſed, and our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ready to releeve them in what we are able.</note> you, and truely to ſay with the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> in the third of his Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, <hi>that I am the man that haue ſeene &amp; felt afflictions, by the rod of Gods wrath.</hi> Alſo I am aboue meaſure forced to ſend forth vnto you, and cry out aloud, to make my grievous deplorable &amp; lamentable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant, knowne vnto you, of the barberous cruelty &amp; tiranies, that Prelates and Iaylors haue for a long time together, and ſtill do, exerciſe vpon mee, labouring by vnheard of cruelty, to take away my life privatly
<note n="(b)" place="margin">This hath been con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stantly their practice, barberouſly to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Saints in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret: knowing their cauſe to be ſo wicked, that if it ſhould come to be openly diſcouered all good men would detest it &amp; them.</note> in a hole and corner, that ſo it might be noyſed abroad, not daring in regard of my vnſpotted innocency, to bring me againe into the publique view of the Kingdome, and therefore doe they tortour my poore weake body, with vnparaleld Paganiſh and Heatheniſh cruelty.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Howſoever wee cannot but greeve to heare of ſuch cruell ſufferings: yet wee maie herein rejoyce, that we ſe theſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſlaves of Antich. ſo farre to fulfill the ſcriptures, as that we may infallibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that they are the <hi>Locuſts</hi> which came out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A breife Relation of part of which, you may read after theſe lines, in my Humble Petition to the Noble Lords for mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, which J ſent the laſt week to the Wardens of the Fleete, having leave of them for a Scribe to write it, and they kept it all night, and Warden <hi>Jugram</hi> ſent me this word back againe: that he would deliuer no Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnles I would recant and ſubmitt.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">That is, turne Papist and ſee he might be ſure to haue liberty enough, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo.</note> J anſwered him back again, that if any of my adverſaries would ſhew mee wherein I had broken any of my Soveraignes Lawes, J would ſubmit without any conditions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12513:3"/>to all that they wovld deſire of mee. Or if they ſee that I am erronious in my Iudgment, J would diſpute it with them, and if they could groundedly, by the authority of the word of God, ſhew and proue, that I hold one errour. I will be bound pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely to recant, in every Citty of the Kingdome. And I ſaid to my Keeper at ſeverall times, and ſo I do ſtill, I deſire no favour at his hands, nor any Biſhop in the Kingdome, for if I be an offender, I deſire the extreamity of the law may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon me to the vtmoſt, for J had rather (I profeſſe vnto you) chuſe to morrow to dy at Tyburne or
<note n="(e)" place="margin">It is no marvaile that the Scotſmen will haue no Biſhops among them. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that aman were put to the cruelst death that could be deviſed, then to be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der their hands.</note> Smithfield, then to bee ſtill induring of my Conſtant Extraordinarie bodily paines and torments, which haue been ſo great, that I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you many times, they haue almoſt diſtracted me of my ſences. And if they will not do this, then ſeeing my owne eſtate is ſpent, and all my kindred hath from the beginning left mee:
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Gods people when they ſuffered vnder the pagans, had this favour ſhewed them: that ther frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds might come freely to them: &amp; ſupply their wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. But the Prelates for cruelty are far worſe then the Heathens, for when they once get a man into their priſon, they will not ſuffer any body to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit him, but rather do ſeeke by ſome ſecret way to murder him.</note> &amp; my weake condition is ſo exceeding chargable vnto me, ſtanding mee in more in one week now, then would keep me fiue weekes if I were wel, And alſo ſeing that any that will take compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my low eſtate, are not ſuffered to come at me, to releeue mee, I deſired the Warden (having none at all to do it for me beſides him) that hee according to his place &amp; office, would truly make my miſerable condition known to to the LORDS, that <hi>J</hi> may haue a competant allowance from them to ſuſtaine nature, that ſo I may not periſh in this deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; weake condition, and this (ſaid I) hee being my chiefe Keeper, hee is bound to do it, at his &amp; your perrell be it, for I know if my innocent blood ſhould this night by cruelty be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaie, the Lord would raiſe vp ſome, that will require of you &amp; him, a ſtrict account how it was ſhed: &amp; though you keep me ſo cloſe, that there be but few at my death, yet you knowe not what great troupes may com to my burial:
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Who ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany thy body to the grave I know not: But this J know An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gels ſhall accompany thy ſoule to Heaven. But as for that blood ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cker Laud: J verily beleeve (except he repent) the Devill will accompany him to hell torment.</note> remember but the late great multitude
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Such a company would follow Laud and his crew If they knew when the king &amp; ſtate would hang them at Tiburne.</note> that came to the Fleet, &amp; attended <hi>M, Burton &amp; M. Prinne</hi> out of the Cittie, and if any thing but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12513:3"/>good follow vpon this, you &amp; hee are the ſole cauſe of it, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as you wil anſwer it before King and State, look to it, for I am my Soveaignes faithfull and leige ſubject
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Let it be obſerve that it was never yee ſeene (nor I hope ſhall be) that ther was any man of his profeſſion iuſtly tainted for a Traitor to the King &amp; cuntry, whereas the Prelates in all ages ſince the Devill erected them haue bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proved the moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious traitors that e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver were in the world, &amp; might iuſttice take place, it would bee proved that they who are now aliue are notorious ones.</note> yea one as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his Crowne as any whatſoever that breathes in all his Dominions, for if it can be proued that ever I broke any of his lawes, I will ſubmit vnto, and ſuffer whatſoever authoritie wil laie vpon mee: therefore be not you &amp; hee the Biſhops Agents to take awaie my life in my cloſe impriſonment, for you vſe me worſe &amp; more tiranically, then ever any traitour in England was vſed, yea worſe then the Gun-powder traitours were vſed. I haue read a great part of the Booke of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> with ſome Hiſtories of the like kinde: and J will meantaine it, that ſuch an vnparaleld Act of crueltie and barborous tiranie, as haue been exerciſed vpon mee, is not to be found in them all. Yea wicked bloodie Bonner
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Seing thier wick ednes is come to ſuch a height, &amp; fulneſſe, and they doe go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond in cruelty the crelſt Tirants that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were: My hope is that their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on &amp; ruin is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. and that hee will cauſe the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſpue them out, and ſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd them packing to their owne place. Amen Amen.</note> himſelfe, never did the like to any of the Saints as haue been done vnto mee, for while they lived, he would either ſuffer their friends to come at them, to releeue them, or elſe he would allow them meantenance to preſerue life in them, but neither of theſe can I enjoy, alſo hee would diſpute with them himſelfe, and ſend for others likewiſe to do it, and vſe all meanes to winne them to himſelfe, but none of theſe haue I yet found, though J haue often deſired it: and promiſed to recant, if it could be ſhewed that I held any errors. Againe hee would take away their lines,
<note n="(l)" place="margin">Without doubt the Prelates would do ſo too, but are reſtrained: Now it is humlby deſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, that they who thinke it not fit that the Biſhops ſhould haue their will in taking our lines away: that they ſuffer them not in the meane time to uſe us worſe.</note> if they broke any of the lawes or would not ſubmit vnto them, but though I haue not broken any of the Kings lawes, and haue offered ſo faire as I haue done, and haue deſired &amp; longed to meet with death, yet can I not be rid of my miſery, but you keep me in a tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<note n="(m)" place="margin">When theſe <hi>Tormentours</hi> feele hell torments, then they will know what it is to torment others,</note> condition, full of extreamitie and bodiliepaine, that I can neither get eaſe ſitting nor lying, being vnable to go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great miſerie, being alwaies as it were in the panges of death, &amp; yet cannot meet with it. But ſaid I to <hi>M. Iohn Murry &amp; M. Morgan</hi> a Papiſt, tell the Warden from mee, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12513:4"/>vnleſſe the Biſhopps, by the law of the land, and the word
<note n="(a)" place="margin">They can ſhew as much word of God for what they doe; as they doe ſhew mercy and goodneſſe in their actions: and that is in both none at all.</note> of God, will ſhew me my offence, I will never ſubmit, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, in the leaſt, while breath is in my body, and therefore it is but in vaine to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe for it, for if he and I ſhould liue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as longe as Methuſalah did, which was almoſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares, yet he ſhould never get mee to goe againſt the ſweet peace of a good conſcience, or recant that which J am perſwaded is a truth, yea if hee ſhould exerciſe all the cruelty in the world upon mee, though he ſhould locke mee in an Iron cheſt, that I could neither ſtirre hand nor foote, and feede me with channell water, and with bread made of ſaw duſt, hee might well take away my life and beeing from the earth, but he ſhould never make me goe, againſt my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for I am kept by the power of God, through faith vnto ſalvation, and Crowne of glory that is ſo rich in my eyes, that I dare not deny Chriſt, nor his truth, though all the crueltie in the world ſhould be inflicted upon mee, leaſt he deny mee before his father, which is in heaven: Yet moſt miſerable it is, that I ſhould periſh by cruelty, in my cloſe condition, being a faithfull ſubject to the King, &amp; neuer broke any of his lawes. And let my tormentors looke to it, as they will anſwer it, for I haue heard that the <hi>Honorable Lords,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Howſoever the Biſhops do cauſe the Godly to be cruelly vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Preſon. Yet I am perſwaded that neither the King nor the Temporall Lords of his majeſties coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, do know of it. For it is not poſſible if they did that they would ſuffer it, conſidering how much it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe cruelty vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any creature: much leſse on man who carries Gods owne image.</note> which haue beene made acquainted with my cruell vſage, proteſted they would not beleeue, that the Warden dealt ſo with mee: this with much more that then I ſaid, with ſome priſoners taking notice of my condition, but eſpecially <hi>Sr. Richard Gravenner,</hi> a worſhipfull Knight,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">J do not marvaile that the knight would not receive it for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth. For the truth is: ſuch is their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty ſhewed to ſuch as are againſt their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that vnles it were ſeen with the eyes, one would ſcarce beleeve it. For this I do affirme &amp; will make it good: that no Rogue in any Iayle of the Land, is ſo baſely &amp; barberouſly handled. Not that the Keepers deſire to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, but are charged ſecretly by the Bb. ſo to do, &amp; threatened to looſe their places if they ſhew favour to them.</note> who ſent to the Warden about it, which I think put him in ſome feare, that he durſt not well denie my reaſonable requeſt, in delivering my petition, ſo hee ſent a ſcribe to me, to draw it oner a gaine, and to leave out the moſt of it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie about my lying in Irons in my ſickneſſe, which I would not leave out,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">This ſhewes that their cruelty is exerciſed only by the Biſhops meanes.</note> only I omitted this clauſe, who ſuffers for his conſcience ſake, which was moſt accepted againſt, and the old
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12513:4"/>women that tends mee, delivered the petition againe to him vpon tueſday laſt, tobedeliuered it to the Lords the next day, but he put me of with delaies, that neither vpon wedneſdaie at night, nor yet vpon thurſdaie could I not in the leaſt know, what was done in it, vntill this preſent Frydaie morning, that my keeper after many ſendings for him, befor he would come at me, told me the Warden had deliuered it to the Clarke of the counſell, but it was not yet anſwered, yea but (ſaid I) was it deliuered to the Lords, and read before them or no, for it may be deliuered to the Clarke of the counſell, and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to their eares, or hands, that I know not ſaith hee, I pray you then tell the Warden, that I deſire to know of him, whither it were delivered to the Lords, yea, or no, or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee will deliuer it, which if he refuſe to doe, I having none to do any thing about it for mee, as hee, and you verie well know, for all my kindred hath left mee, in regard the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hop of Canterburie,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Was there ever ſuch a Tiran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heard o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: that ſeekes to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do whole families, for the mallace which he beares to ſome perticu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lar perſons. If there were nothing elſe to ſtirre up the hearts of people againſt him this were enough.</note> in reveng, hath fallen upon my Father, about his outward eſtate, hauing now for a longe time together, beene in ſuit, for all his land, which ſuit hath coſt him many a thouſand pound, and hath beene heard before the King, and Nobles, and all the Iudges of the land, and the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hop
<note n="(b)" place="margin">I know not how that Judge did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the <hi>Caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> J ſhould ſay <hi>Kan kerbury:</hi> But if I had heard him ſpeak it. J ſhould haue ſet my eyes upon him, and ſaid unto him as <hi>Paul</hi> did to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imas the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer, O full of all ſuttilty, and all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, thou child of the Divell, thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy of all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, wilt thou not ceaſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the right ways of the Lord.</hi>
               </note> in priuate, hath ſpoken to the Iudges of the Circuit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Father, for my ſake, which one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> told my eldeſt Brother of, and this hath bred mee a ſore affliction, from all my kindred, but eſpeciallie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my Father
<note n="(c)" place="margin">This is on of their common practiſes: to ſet the father againſt the ſonne, the King against the Subject. But Chriſt will ſet himſelfe againſt them one day.</note>, which hath made him write to my youngeſt Brother, here in London, to beware of mee, and my ſtepps, for I haue beene the greateſt griefe vnto him, that ever came to him, ſoe that I haue noe friend left that I know of, to follow it for mee.</p>
            <p>Therefore in regard the Warden deales ſo with me, J ſhall be forced to proclaime abroad &amp; make the Kingdome ring
<note n="(d)" place="margin">The Kingdome rings enough already with the Prelates cruelty, for they are minded by all ſorts of people good &amp; had, a most bloody generation: inſomuch as the nation is wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of them: &amp; deſire to he rid of them, as of their ſoreſt &amp; greatest plague,</note>, with his and the Prelaes cruelty towards mee, ſeing they ſtill do, as formerly they haue done; by all meanes poſſible, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12513:5"/>my Iuſt and murnefull complaint, might not come vnto the <hi>Honorable Lords</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">This hath beene their conſtant prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: to keepe from the King and State their ſecret &amp; bloody acts: for they wel know that if it ſhould be known how many they make away in Priſon, by hard vſage: they wold ſmart for it.</note> eares, and therefore I muſt be conſtrained to condeavour to get one delivered whether he will or no, and make him it may be, ſmart for his vnwarrantable cruelty, that hee inhumanly hath exerciſed vpon mee, not only ſince I came into your cuſtody, but alſo before: who kept me cloſe priſoner, well nigh foure monthes together, before my cruell publique ſuffering, and would not ſuffer me to take the ayre, the ſpace of one houre: though <hi>J</hi> haue often ſent to him and deſired it. For which cloſe impriſonment, hee himſelfe told me, hee had no order from the <hi>Lords,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Hee meanes the Temporall Lords. for doubtles he knew that it was the Prelates deſire, that he ſhould vſe him as Cruellie as could be: beſides I do beleeve, that were it not to giue them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, no keeper in the Land would ſhew ſoe much inhumanity &amp; barberouſnes as ſome doe.</note> neither would he ſhew me any, but ſaid all my puniſhment was little enough for me: becauſe I was ſo refractory and ſtubborne, when before his face J deſired to know wherin, &amp; this J will depoſe vpon my oath before <hi>King &amp; State.</hi> For (hee) I verily beleeue kept me vp at the Biſhops private inſtagation,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Thou mayſt be ſure of that. for is there any baſenſſe vſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Gods people: but they are cheife cauſers of it.</note> but coloured it over with another pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: becauſe J was not able to procure two Aldermens fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, according to his demande, of two thouſand pouud bond, for my ſafe impriſonment, when he had me vnder many locks, &amp; I being as peaceable a priſoner as any in the Fleete.</p>
            <p>This and much more of his cruelty exeriſed vpon me from time to time, as J am able larglie to particular, which I thinke he will not be able to anſwer, &amp; therfore he dares nor let my miſerable eſtate be made known vnto the <hi>Lords,</hi> for feare he himſelfe ſmart ſoundly for it, being a maine cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>But tell him from mee, that I am almoſt murdered with cruelty, my ſtrength being gone and my life euen at deaths doore. therefore J do proteſt in the preſence of God, if I haue not ſpeedy redreſſe oue way or another, I will proclaime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loude his &amp; the Prelates wickednes &amp; barberous tyrany.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">And know this for thy comfort that many thouſands of vs, do cry aloud in thy behalfe; &amp; for many other ſufferers with thee, vnto the Lord, that he would avenge himſelfe on his enimies. And J beleeve Gods wrath is not farre from them.</note> &amp; I dovbt not but to make him and them ſmart for it: ſeeing he will not according to his place (the <hi>Lords</hi> having ſent to him &amp; my <hi>Doctour:</hi> to know how it is with mee) make them truely
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12513:5"/>acquainted how ſubmiſſiue I am to any reaſonable demande, as I declared to his face when I was laſt before him, but ſeekes by cruelty to take away my life: hoping in regard of my great weaknes and paine, that <hi>J</hi> will ſuddenly die, and there wilbe an end of me. And then may ſaie
<note n="[a]" place="margin">This hath beene anciently their prac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tice when they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Saints in priſon by barbarous uſage; to deviſe noto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious lyes for their excuſe, but the Lord who ſees their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe will bring them forth one day for it, to their ſhame before men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</note> I dyed of long ſicknes and weakneſſe, and ſo colour over their tyrany and crueltie, for he dares not let his and the Biſhops crueltie be knowne, but ſeeks by all means to hide it from the <hi>Noble Lords</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">No doubt the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble Lords &amp; Peeres doe know a great deal of their treache<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, &amp; villany: yet not halfe of it, for it is one of their ſpeciall imployme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to keep from the King and ſtate the knowledge of their baſe actions, and hence it is that they ſtriue ſoe much to ſuppreſſe al books that are writen in the diſcouery of their actions, for they wel known, ſhould the land know what they doe it would ſpue them out.</note> &amp; <hi>Peeres</hi> of the Land, whom I know haue more Humanity, Nobilitie and mercie in their heroycall breaſt: then for nothing &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any juſt offence, to take awaie a poore young mans life in a corner. Now the very ſpeaking of theſe things (to ſome of my compaſſionate friends, that came vp to my lodging to ſe me, who would receiue no wrong of my Keeper) hath ſtruck him to the very heart, and made him looke ſoe paile as if he would haue fallen down dead at my bed ſide, &amp; it ſo affrighted him: that now he will not let any come to me, but hath refuſed to let many come at me, that haue deſired to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate to my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſities, neither can I now ſcarce get himſelfe to come vp to mee. But (ſaith hee) that which you ſet your hand too, (before <hi>Sr. John Bankes</hi>) hath vndone you, well if it haue (ſaid I) yet I am ſure there is nothing in it, either againſt the <hi>King</hi> or his lawes Its true I accuſed the Biſhops of High Treaſon,
<note n="[c]" place="margin">So much hath beene from time to time offered to bee proued, in the chiefeſt Courts of the Land, yea if ſome parliament had ſtood they would haue been ere this time cenſured &amp; executed for Traytors, &amp; this they know well enough, inſomuch as a Parliament; to them, is as <hi>Drake</hi> was to the Spaniard.</note> &amp; mentioned the Parliament lawes of the Land for proofe of it. Alſo their publique renouncing of the <hi>King</hi> and State, in the Cenſure of <hi>Noble Doctor Bastwick,</hi> in the High Commiſſion Court. And <hi>J</hi> offered vpon my life to make it good, and this I ſpake. alſo before many Priſoners through the grates of my window, deſiring them beare wittneſſe of this: and much more which I then ſpake, and now againe to you my Brethren; vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well what I ſay, and J will affirme it: that all the Biſhops in England that had a hand in the Cenſuring of <hi>Dr. Baſtwick</hi> in the High Commiſſion Court, are Traytours to the <hi>King</hi> &amp;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12513:6"/>
               <hi>State,</hi> as I will proue by ſeverall Acts of Parliamet, vpon paine of looſing my head; if I may haue a legall proceeding againſt them. Therefore make it knowne:
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Jt is made known to the whole nation, and proved clearely in many Bookes, as the <hi>Abreviate Syons Plea,</hi> &amp;c. Beſides the people generally take them no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</note> for hee that conceales Treaſon, (by the lawes of the Land) is guilty of puniſhment, as well as the Traitour himſelfe, therefore looke to it, for J am able to proue what J ſay. But as for my <hi>Petition,</hi> J am out of all hopes of any releefe by it, in regard it is not yet, neither do I think it wil ever be delivered to the <hi>Lords</hi> by the Warden. And alſo I do verily thinke it will be found, that hee and the Biſhops as J haue accuſed them before mauy witneſſes: even the ſame day fell ſicke, and as J haue formerly ſaid, they haue conſpired together, by tiranicall cruelty, of ſet purpoſe to take awaie my life and blood, which is almoſt ſpent alreadie that ſo I might not liue to make (their Pagan like wickednes and barberous tirnanie) knowne. And therefore was I laid in Irones for a long time together, even in my ſickneſſe, in which I laid night and day, with my hands and feet faſt in the Fetters, my Bootes &amp; ſtockens being on my legs for many nights together, Without (I verilie thinke,) the leaſt order from the <hi>Honorable, Lords,</hi> they hoping by this meanes, to put an end to my daies, which they haue almoſt done. For as I then tould my <hi>Doctor,</hi> the coldneſſe of my Irones, they being verie ſtraite vpon the wriſts of my Armes, which ſtruck an ague ſoe to my heart, that J thought I ſhould haue dyed in a ſudden fitt of paine. when none was with mee, and I verily thinke it had killed me ere this, if I had not followed my <hi>Doctours</hi> adviſe, in being at charges to get a wider made, which ſent for to the Smiths, my Keeper delaying to do it for mee, though I much deſired it of him: that ſo I might haue wrapped cloaths enough about it, to keep awaie the peircing cold, which proceeded from the coldneſſe of the Irones.
<note n="(b)" place="margin">It is a thing which the Prelates doe much labour about, namely to per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwade the King and his Councill that the Puritants in writings againſt their cruelty do greatly diſgrace the Government of the Land. But if the thing were truly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; that which hath made the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh nation Contemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tible in the eyes of the world, is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane practiſes of Biſhoppes, for where ſhall a man heare of ſo vile and bloody a practice as this.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O yee Heavens and earth, that is to ſay: you true Churches &amp; Chriſtian Common wealths, (as you are called) ſtand amazed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12513:6"/>and wonder: at the barberous and ſavadge crueltie, (of bloody Biſhops &amp; Iaylours) exerciſed vpon mee, a poore weake and young ſtripling, without any juſt cauſe at al, only becauſe I love the Lord Ieſus Chriſt &amp; am a faithfull ſubject to my Prince,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Were thou not a faithfull ſubject to thy Prince, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates would never hate thee, for what Prieſt or Ieſuit haue they ever ſo ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled.</note> &amp; Country, and wil not ſuffer (as much as in me lies) to be ruina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by Ambitious, Treacheros popiſh Prelats. For if my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of bodie (which is now exceeding weake) would ſerue, and a fit oppertunity, I could write a large &amp; Lamentable complaint vnto you, that one would hardly beleeue:
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Yes? many would beleeve it. For it is certain, &amp; I here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it of knowledg; that in all the Popiſh countries where I haue beene, there is not that cruelty now exerciſed by Biſ. any where, as there is in England. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in Poland, Spaine, France, are not halfe ſo vile. Much leſſe ſinne as thoſe doe againſt knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> that ever ſuch barberous crueltie ſhould (be in England) vpon a poor weak and innocent young man. Now this may make your ſpirits within you to faile: in rememberance of your great ſinne &amp; want of courage,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">It is iuſt vvith God, that he ſhould keepe theſe <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> amongſt us: as pricks in our ſide, in regard wee ſhew not our ſelves more zealous of his glory in the releefe of our Brethren.</note> in looking to me in my great &amp; ſore ſickneſſe, that you laboured not for ſome redreſſe for mee; who haue ſuffered al that I haue done, for the glorie of God, and your good and welfare, to free you from bloody tiranicall Lordly Prelates. Oh therefore remember what the Angell of the Lord ſaid, <hi>Iudgs</hi> 5. <hi>Curſe ye Meroze with a bitter curſe, becauſe the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants thereof came not out to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> And the ſpirit of God in <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 48. ſaith, <hi>Curſed be he that doth the work of the Lord negligently &amp; careleſly.</hi> Now you being the Lords people, you are bound to do his worke: and to ſecond thoſe that do it,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they who haue brauely fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſh. had beene followed my minde giues me they had been dovvn ere this time, I do not meane any fighting vvith carnall Weapons, but profeſſing openly and boldly the truth, and ſuffering chearfully for it.</note> to the vtmoſt of your power. But how you haue failed in doing this duty of loue to mee, judg yee, for I am now in <hi>Pauls</hi> condition when hee firſt anſwered before <hi>Nero,</hi> had none to ſtand by him, but all forſooke him. Ah my Brethren if at the laſt there be any couraige in you for Chriſt and his truth, or any bowels of mercie and compaſſion in you towards mee, his faithfull and innocent ſervant that ſuffers for his truth, I humblie beſeech &amp; intreate you to looke with loue and a fauourable eye vpon my low eſtate, and ſuffer me not to looſe my life in a hole and corner, and ſo periſh in my deplorable condition. Which if you do not looke the better to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12513:7"/>mee, to make mee ſome ſpeedy helpe, otherwiſe I am like ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to looſe my life, for I do proteſt in the preſence of my God from my verie ſoule, that I am dailie affraid, that I ſhall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatelie be murdered,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">There be many that do think ſo too; and haue an eye at thy condition. Now if things fall not out wel; we do not doubt but juſtice will yet take place amongſt us, if not the Lord will right the poore mans caſe.</note> by ſecret cruel practiſes from <hi>William Laud</hi> the great Prelate and traytour of Canterburie, &amp; <hi>Iames Jugram</hi> the cruell tinannicall corrupt <hi>Machavillion</hi> warden of the Freete. And therefore once more for our Chriſt his ſake J earneſtlie deſire you, that ſome of you would by all faire &amp; peaceable meanes, labour for ſome redreſſe for mee, by taking this my following petition, to deliuer to the King,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Oh, that it vvould pleaſe his Majeſtie but to here once the caſe of his poor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and to take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvhat they ſuffer at the hands of the Prelates. I am perſvvaded, vvere he rightly poſſeſſed of their doings, hee vvould be ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putting forth his little ſinger to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them in Scotland, as that he vvould ſoone vvith both hands caſt them out of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> or to the Lords, and acquaint them if it bee poſſible trulie and throughly with my deplorable miſerie and lamentable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to the ſhame of England, &amp; all true hearted Engliſh men, I am like for my innocencie to be murdered in my cloſe, cruell impriſonment, hauing to my knowledge, never broken any of my Soveraignes lawes; or diſobeied anie, that are in lawfull autoritie, which if it can be proued againſt mee, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſubmit, to whatſoever they will deſire of me. I know they haue uſed much meanes, that my petitions ſhould not haue audience, therefore I praie you, be not repulſed at the firſt deniall, but let your importunitie giue them no reſt, and I doubt not, but to haue redreſſe, to the confuſion of my capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call enemies the Prelates, which if you out of baſe, &amp; fearfull cowardlines refuſe
<note n="(c)" place="margin">The covvardlines and fainthartedneſſe of our nation, is that which hath made the Prelats to domineer ſo ouer us, now what ſlaue would not take authority vpon him, if his Mr. giue way to it.</note> to do, it it is your great ſin, for ſaith the ſpirit of God. Curſed is he that is affraid of the face of man: and I know, If I periſh in this my forſaken condition, my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud will lie heavie upon your heads, who haue neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected your dutie towards mee, In this particular, all that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire at the King,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">J hope if the King and counſell be made acquainted with it, they will ſee to it as that the blood of this young man may not ly upon the Land.</note> &amp; Nobles hands is, but the one of theſe 3. things, which yet in England was never denied to anie traitour.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Jf I be an offender, and deſerued death, I refuſe not to dy, but deſire that it may be inflicted upon mee, in a legal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12513:7"/>way to the utmoſt, without any mercy at all.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Were a man a murderer a Trayter a Witch, &amp;c. What could the magiſtrate doe more then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by law: Now conſider the cruelty of the Prelates, vvho ſeek to haue the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt in a more cruell vvay.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If not this, then that my friends that would take compaſſion on me, might be ſuffered with freedome to come at me, to relieve mee.
<note n="(b)" place="margin">It is ſuch a cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as vvas never heard of in the vvorld to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any Tirants but the Prelates. Namly, to ſhut men up in noyſome Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, &amp; forbid all people to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any releefe. It vvere unmercifull to ſhut up any bruit beaſt &amp; not giue it food, for a man vvould rather kill it out of the vvay, then tiraniſe ouer it in ſuch a ſort.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, if this neither, then ſeeing I am at extraordinarie charges, in regard of my ſickneſſe, and weakneſſe; and my eſtate is ſpent, my humble deſire is, that they would allow me a competent allowance, to ſuſtaine nature, &amp; preſerue life.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">No doubt if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King or the Councill, vnderſtand what is here deſired, but they will grant it, for vnleſſe they be Biſhops, an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man is mercifull by nature.</note> Jt may be the anſwere to my petition, may by the cunning of the ſuttle fox of Lambeth, who hitherto hath ſtopped and intercepted all meanes, that haue beene uſed for my redreſſe, both to the King, and Nobles. Therefore I earneſtly deſire of you, that ſo me of you would dailie come to my pittifull Purga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torie &amp; inquire how 'tis with me, &amp; whether I be devoured in the flames thereof or no, for the Biſhops tirannicall crueltie, and inveterate hatred againſt me, and my jaylors doggedneſſe, and ſavageneſſe is ſuch, that I do aſſure you upon the word of a true and faithfull ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt, that I feare, if you neglect me, as you haue done, and do not looke well after mee, in hauing a daily vigilant eye, to the fleete, I ſhall ſhortly by one meanes or other, haue my life taken from me, in a corner, therefore as you loue my Maiſter Chriſt, haue brotherly care of me, his faithfull ſervant.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not neede (I hope) in this my exceeding great weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hauing gone alreadie beyond my preſent ſtrength, in a halfe blinde condition, to write theſe lines my ſelfe, without Inke unto you, being aboue meaſure preſſed in my ſpirit to do it, inregard I am ſo exceeding tormented with bodilie Paine, eſpecially in my head by reaſon of my long cloſeneſſe, and the crueltie that I under went in the daie of my publicke ſuffering, that my ſoule is not able to containe it ſelfe, in ſilence any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſeaſt I become guiltie of my owne blood. To laie down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more arguments vnto you; but deſire you to read two late
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12513:8"/>printed bookes, the one is called <hi>The Beast is Wounded. Or the Scots Newes,</hi> and put forth by <hi>Iohu Baſtwicks</hi> Younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note n="[a]" place="margin">It is pitty that young Baſtwick puts not forth more bookes, but it may be he hopes their ruin is at hand, &amp; in that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gard thinkes it not neceſſary to write.</note> &amp; the other is Called <hi>A Light for the ignorant.</hi> And in them you ſhal find your dutie punctually laid down how to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt the wicked Lordlie Bb. as the Divel himſelf whoſe officers they are, &amp; with all lawfull power, to keep, &amp; aſſiſt thoſe that groan under their tirannie, &amp; in a lawful &amp; right waie ſeeke deliuerance from them. So remembring my brotherly loue vnto you, and returning my humbleſt thankes vnto you for your loue alreadie manifeſted vnto mee; and beſtowed vpon mee, for which the Lord hath a recompence in ſtore. My ſoule now lying a bleeding before my God,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">That which giues us caſe to think that their curſed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is comming down: It is in regard of the many effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prayers which are dayly put up to God againſt them, and it is obſerued how the Lord doth in a ſpeciall manner now moue the harts of his Children this way to ſeek him, as if he meant to prepare away by their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for to bring in his judgments upon the Kingdom of the Beaſt.</note> earneſtlie, and unceſſantlie crying vnto him with manie teares proceeding from a too too much burdened and wounded ſpirit, and his Sion, and the downfall of all Gods enimies, which he for his mercies ſake haſten and accompliſh.</p>
            <p>Now vnto Iehovah, the Lord of Hoſts, and our faithfull and powerfull God, I committ and commend you, &amp; reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From the Fleete, my refining furnace, in which though my ſoule thriue in Godlineſſe: yet my bodie and blood is almoſt ſpent. <date>This preſent Friday, being one of the Biſhops Idoll-daies, commonly called, St. <hi>Thomas-day. December</hi> 20. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your faithfull &amp; courraigious Brother, in great tribulation for the purity of the truth of Chriſt, and publique bearing witneſſe theretoo, <hi>JOHN LILBVRNE. Etatis ſuae</hi> 22.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The fore-mentioned <hi>Petition</hi> followes.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:12513:8"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lords, and others, of his Majestyes moſt Honourable privie Councill.</head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>IOHN LILBVRNE</hi> Cloſe priſoner in the Common Jayle in the Fleete.</head>
            <p>HVmbly ſheweth, that your Petitioner hath beene about ten moneths cloſe priſoner, the greateſt part whereof hath been in the wards of the Fleete, where hee hath beene ſo cloſely kept, that no friends haue beene ſuffered to come at him, to reliefe him; to ſpeake with him. And alſoe for a great time together, hath layen in letters of Iron, vpon both handes and legs, and ſo it hath pleaſed God, inregard of the exceeding greatneſſe of his ſore puniſhment, and miſery which he hath layen under, to bring bodily weakneſſe upon him, and a heavy and dangerous ſickneſſe, which he hath laid many moneths together, which hath brought him many times even to deaths doore, which yet with weakneſſe and patience, hee hath undergone, though hee rather hath deſired to haue choſen preſent death, then to haue felt the conſtant bitternes, of thoſe bodily torments, &amp; paines; which in this miſerable condition, he hath groned vnder.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as your petitioner hath in all humble manner beſought his Majeſty, and your Honours, for a little liberty to take ſome aire for the preſeruation of his life, but no anſwere could he receiue, being now out of all hopes, to obtaine his humble, and reaſonable requeſt, yet remaines as cloſe as ever, in which regard he hath continued very weake, and in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding much bodily paine and miſery: being forced in this his weaknes, to keepe the coldneſſe of his Irons from his Tender fleſh, to lye for a long time together in his bed, in ſtockings and bootes, which ſicknes in regard of the greatnes, and long continuance of it, and being forced to a conſtant courſe of Phyſick, and to keepe a dyet of Phiſicall things, to keepe life in his body which hath beene extraordinary chargeable to him, and hath exhauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſpent all his eſtate, and being from the firſt beginning unto this day forſaken by his kindred and friends and left to the world.</p>
            <p>Hee is therefore forced in regard of want of meanes, to keepe life &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain nature in this his ſicknes. To Petition moſt humbly to your honours, that out of compaſſion to him, in his great diſtreſſe, who ſuffers for his conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence ſake) in which he is like to periſh, to grant him a competent allowance, to preſerue life, that he may not dye for want of food. And as in duty bound ſhall ever pray.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
